<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Mamora, or, A summary relation sent to the king of Spaine of the good successe of a voyage which it hath pleased God to giue in taking, and suprising, of Mamora, a port in Barbary. By the armado and hoast royall, of the ocean sea, whereof was captaine generall Don Luis Faxardo: assisted with three galleis [sic] of Portingall, vnder the command of the Conde de Elda, and fiue gallies of Spaine, vnder the Duke of Fernandina.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06793</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104451</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840189</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840189</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4665</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06793)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4665)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 851:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Mamora, or, A summary relation sent to the king of Spaine of the good successe of a voyage which it hath pleased God to giue in taking, and suprising, of Mamora, a port in Barbary. By the armado and hoast royall, of the ocean sea, whereof was captaine generall Don Luis Faxardo: assisted with three galleis [sic] of Portingall, vnder the command of the Conde de Elda, and fiue gallies of Spaine, vnder the Duke of Fernandina.</title>
                  <author>Squire, William, fl. 1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by N. Okes] for Thomas Archer, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes-head Pallace, neere the Royall-exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>A translation, by William Squire, from the original Spanish.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴(-B4).</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pirates --  Morocco --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Hijacking of ships --  Morocco --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mehdia (Morocco) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4665:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:4665:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <p>Newes from Mamora, <hi>OR,</hi> A Summary Relation ſent to the <hi>King of Spaine of the good ſucceſſe of a</hi> Voyage, which it hath pleaſed GOD to giue in taking, and ſurpriſing, of Mamora, a Port in Barbary.</p>
            <p>By the Armado and Hoaſt Royall, of the Ocean Sea, whereof was Captaine General <hi>Don Luis Faxardo:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ASSISTED</hi> With three Galleis of Portingall, vnder the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the <hi>Conde de Elda,</hi> and fiue Gallies <hi>of Spaine, vnder the Duke of Fernandina.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>fleur-de-lis</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Popes-head Pallace, neere the Royall-Exchange. 1614.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:4665:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:4665:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>of late there came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hands a Relation, written in Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, of the ſurpriſing of <hi>Mamora,</hi> a Port in Barbary, by the Army of the King of Spaine, as by that which enſueth more at large appeareth, which at the requeſt of ſome friends I Tranſlated, and with all thought it neceſſary to aduertiſe thee, that heerein I reſpected not ſo much exactneſſe in Tranſlating word for word out of the Originall, (whereby the matter muſt perforce looſe its garb and graine) as I haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuored to declare the preciſe truth of each paſſage, according to the authors methode and intention.</p>
            <p>I was the rather induced to giue thee notice, for that, happily, ſome that are curious, and intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent, in that language, comparing this with ſome Copies, or Manuſcripts of this buſineſſe, might taxe my fidelity, or vnderſtanding: which to preuent, I inſerted this briefe aduertiſment, which with the diſcourſe it ſelfe, I referre to thy peruſall, thy ſelfe to GOD, and my ſelfe to thy good opinion:</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London <date>the 28. of September: 1614.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>W. Squ.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:4665:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:4665:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            <head>A Summary Relation ſent to the <hi>King of Spaine of the good ſucceſſe of a Voyage, which it hath pleaſed</hi> GOD <hi>to</hi> giue, in the taking and ſurpriſing of <hi>Mamora,</hi> a Port in Barbary.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt of <hi>Auguſt, 1614.</hi> there ſet ſaile out of the Bay of <hi>Cadiz</hi> 99. Saile of Veſſels of warre great and ſmall, the ſaid Gallies being part of them.</p>
            <p>Within two daies After they came in the fight of <hi>Alarache,</hi> white the ſaid Army was diſcouered by the naturall Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Coaſt, which could not be auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by reaſon of calmes and contrary w<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ds And hereaboutes there was aduice giuen by <hi>Garſper de Valdes,</hi> maiſter of the fie<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a ſhore, vnto thoſe of the Army, that as yet there was not any news or ſuſpicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſhore of any thing.</p>
            <p>The day following, in the euening, the ſaid Army arriued before <hi>Mamora,</hi> and came to an Anchor without reach of Shot, a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t a league of, for that the tyde ſerued not to go in. At the ſaid ancoring place, the army found three ſhips of Warre appertaining to the
<pb facs="tcp:4665:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->States of <hi>Holland;</hi> the Generall whereof was <hi>Iohn <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Kings Armado, and did ſuch other cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies and ſalutations as any Vaſſals of his Maieſty ought to do.</p>
            <p>Then the Generall of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> gaue to vnderſtand to thoſe of the Armado, that there were within the Port of <hi>Mamora 15.</hi> Saile of Pirates, who perceiuing themſelues ſhut vp within the ſaid Port, ſo long time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to grow deſperate, and ſent forth a meſſenger with words and threatnings, that they were now reſolued to come forth and fight with the ſaid <hi>Hollanders,</hi> with which meſſage the Flemings were not very well pleaſed, notwithſtanding there came then a fourth ſhip of their company (which the ſaid Army left riding in <hi>Cadiz</hi> at their ſetting forth) and ioyned with the afore-ſaid three <hi>Hollanders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed the Flemmings forces were but weake; and therefore they ſeemed to be well contented to ſee his Maieſties forces ſo ſtrong, and by that meanes to be acquitted of their obligation and attendance there, which was for the letters of the King <hi>Muley Sydan,</hi> in anſwere to certaine letters, written vnto him by the <hi>Graue Maurice,</hi> who as is thought had written to the ſaid <hi>Muly Sydan,</hi> that with his conſent; hel<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and fa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> might poſſeſſe that Port for the States: For ſuch, or like conſiderations, the ſaid Generall
<pb facs="tcp:4665:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uented: for <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oy<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing with <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (contrary to his own<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſire) and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> he <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 paragraph">
                  <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing the great impoſſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lities and difficulties falling out that day, it was thought fit to retire, and the rather, for that in attempting to land men in the plaine, or ſands of the ſhore there was found the like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences,
<pb facs="tcp:4665:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo much as they were almoſt out of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>  con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that by occaſion of the aforeſaid lets and impe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iments the enemies on land had three daies time, to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and bring downe the Inhabitants thereabouts as indeed they did, howbeit in ſuch actions oftentimes, the Almighty power yeeldeth hope, and helpe, beyond <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xpectation.</p>
            <p>The fifth day <hi>dito,</hi> being the day of our Lady <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſea <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, ſo as the Army beganne to view and attempt the barre and landing places, and committed the effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>of for the ſide towards Ala<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ach, vnto Captaine <hi>Ioſephide Men<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> Captaine of the Generall Gallio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, whom notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he was <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> three times in great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of drowning did finde out amongſt the ſho<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les and ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nds a place of about ſome 100 yar<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s where in a calme, men might get on land<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Howbeit it is preſumed neuer any lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded there before. Now ſeeing the weather ſomewhat faire, hee returned, and propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Army to land there, where the d<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger might be (<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ely) the drowning of ſome men; whiles others might land, by wading vp to the middle, and per<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es ſome Bo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tes might be <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in the landing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Vpon the ſaid information, they reſolued vpon that courſe, and therefore did take occaſion preſently to depart and take leaue of the Generall of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd his Captaines, who at that
<pb facs="tcp:4665:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->inſtant were viſiting and ſaluting the Generall of the Armado aboard the Captaine reall, and now ready to returne aboard their owne Hulkes; thoſe of the Army not once acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſaid Hollanders of their laſt reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, although the Flemmings omitted not to enquire thereof, as iudging now that the oportunity was vtterly for further attempt in that enterpriſe.</p>
            <p>This done, thoſe of the Armado went euery man about their buſineſſe, with ſuch ſpeed and indeuour, that almoſt before the Hollanders had gotten aboard their ſhips, there were ſuddenly landed, a thouſand <hi>Spaniards,</hi> without the loſſe of more then one man, and not a Boate, which ſeemed a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, ſeeing the great dangers and diffculties occurring.</p>
            <p>Then a Maiſter of the field called <hi>Iero<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo de Auguſtin,</hi> and Captaine <hi>Chriſtopher Lechuga,</hi> (who executed the office of <hi>Maiſtro de Campo</hi> Generall) lead forth the Vant-gard, both of them ſhewing great valour and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence.</p>
            <p>The firſt of the Army that leapt a ſhore, was Captaine <hi>Bartholmew Garcia de Nadall,</hi> Captaine <hi>Ioſeph de Mena,</hi> and <hi>Don Fermyn de Codoza,</hi> and <hi>Anducha:</hi> And the firſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient that got on land, was that of <hi>Don Charles de Ibarra</hi> together with his owne perſon.</p>
            <p>Then did the <hi>Conde de Elda,</hi> and the
<pb facs="tcp:4665:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->
               <hi>Duque de Fernandina,</hi> place the prowes of their Gallies, ſo neere the landing place, that with their Artilery, they might cleere and command all the Moriſh Horſe-men a ſhore, in ſuch ſort as they retired and gaue place to thoſe of the Armado to forme their ſquadron, which done, they hoped the buſineſſe well neere effected, then the ſaid Squadron mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſwiftly towards the aforeſaid ſmall Fort, where finding but little defence of the entry, they tooke it preſently.</p>
            <p>The Captaine <hi>Don Charles de Ibarra,</hi> and <hi>Gaſper Gonſalues,</hi> with their Companies, lead the Vant-gard, and the firſt that entred the Fort, as is ſaid, was Captaine <hi>Peter de Garreta,</hi> an <hi>entertenido</hi> or Souldier be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Kings Armado. There they wonne three peeces of Ordinance which the Pirates had left ſpiked vp, but not ſo well but that the ſaid <hi>Ioſeph de Mena,</hi> beganne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to make vſe of them, diſcharging vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Moores that lay vpon the other ſide of the Riuer, and being horſemen did great ſpoyle amongſt them. At the time that this was doing it fell out as if it paſſed in fight the one of the other, that the Captaine <hi>Vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaball</hi> ſhot alſo from aboard the Admirall: and about euening the newes heereof came to the Moores that were on the other ſide defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the barre with a great number of Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, and Harquebuſhers, in ſo much that they left their Trenches and Ordinance, and
<pb facs="tcp:4665:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->burnt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ips and not a man <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The day following which w<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the day of the Tranſfiguration, and the ſixth of Auguſt, poſſeſſion was taken of the Port, and the Vaunt-gard of the Fleet was led by the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the <hi>Duque de Fernandina,</hi> and the Reare by the <hi>Conde de Elda,</hi> accompanied with fifty Saile of ſhips great and ſmall.</p>
            <p>There were riding in the Riuer ten Saile, or Veſſels more which the enemies could not burne: Aboard them <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as ſome goods, but of ſmall importance, the enemy hauing carried all away that was of valew; And for the Pirates although they were ſent vnto, and profered, in his Maieſties name to accept of vſage correſpondent to good warres, they would not accept thereof, nor truſt thereunto, Rather in ſteed of ſhewing gratuity they dealt ill and did put to the ſword ten or twelue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that were ſent vnto them vnder aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to treat with them, which ill dealing they haue paid, as it is reported by diuers priſoners of ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dry Nations found here, for that the Moores did by and by ſet vpon the ſaid Pirats, and robbed and ſpoyled them moſt cruelly.</p>
            <p>This done, thoſe of the Army poſſeſſ themſelues of the Mountaine or high ground on <hi>Saly</hi> ſide, which is the moſt eminent place: And from thence the ſame euening, Trenches were opened to ſuccour and lodge the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and care taken in the choiſe of the conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nienteſt
<pb facs="tcp:4665:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->place for fortification and keeping of the barre and ancoring place.</p>
            <p>There a Well of reaſonable good ware was found, and more they looke and hope for.</p>
            <p>This Port of <hi>Mamora,</hi> is the beſt and moſt <hi>Abrigado,</hi> or well ſcituated, of any in Europe, howbeit the barre it ſelfe at high water is not aboue eight <hi>Godos</hi> in depth, which is not draught ſufficient for great Gallions, but there may well enter ſhippes of three or foure hundred Tunnes, ſuch as is one of thoſe wee tooke, and as another which a French-man ſtole out of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Admirall Generall. <hi>Don In<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Faxardo de Gueurra,</hi> the Admirall <hi>Diego de S. Turbe.</hi> The Gouernour <hi>Int. de Lara,</hi> Captaine <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian Granero,</hi> Lieutenant of the Captaine Generall of the Artilery, haue done and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed what concerned them with great care and deligence, the Countadors <hi>Signior In<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. de Barundial,</hi> and <hi>Franſiſco Beltran de Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronda</hi> and all the other Offirers haue not bene ſlacke, but haue performed their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            <p>This day Maſſe was ſaid a ſhore, and thankes giuen to <hi>GOD,</hi> to whom all ought to bee attributed, whom no doubt will fauour this action, as his owne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:4665:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->
Of what elſe occurreth accompt ſhall bee giuen.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Written in the Port of <hi>Mamora,</hi> 
                  <date>the ſeuenth of Auguſt. 1614.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <byline>Tranſlated out of Spaniſh by <hi>W. Squire.</hi>
            </byline>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
